<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The toutch-stone of mony and commerce: or an expedient for increase of trade mony, and shiping in England. Shewing also how the arrears of the army, and other publique debts, may be forthwith satisfied, without laying more impositions upon the people, or burthen on trade. Together with custome and excise regulated. Wherein is manifest the destruction of trade, by its irregular mannagement at present: with means to prevent the like inconvenience from time to come. By S. E. A lover of his country.</title>
            <author>S. E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E41</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834517</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834517</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39018</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39135)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1810:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The toutch-stone of mony and commerce: or an expedient for increase of trade mony, and shiping in England. Shewing also how the arrears of the army, and other publique debts, may be forthwith satisfied, without laying more impositions upon the people, or burthen on trade. Together with custome and excise regulated. Wherein is manifest the destruction of trade, by its irregular mannagement at present: with means to prevent the like inconvenience from time to come. By S. E. A lover of his country.</title>
                  <author>S. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed at the authors charge, for his countries good: and are to be sold at the Turcks Head in Corn-hill, near the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1654].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing CD-ROM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Commerce --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:39018:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:39018:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Toutch-Stone of MONY and COMMERCE: Or an Expedient For increaſe of <hi>Trade, Mony,</hi> and <hi>Shiping</hi> In <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing alſo how the Arrears of the <hi>Army,</hi> and other Publique Debts, may be forthwith Satisfied, without laying more Impoſitions upon the People, or Burthen on Trade.</p>
            <p>Together with <hi>CVSTOME</hi> and <hi>EXCISE REGVLATED.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is manifeſt the Deſtruction of Trade, by its Irregular mannagement at preſent: with means to prevent the like Inconvenience for time to come.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. E.</hi> A Lover of his Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at the Authors Charge, for his Countries good: and are to be ſold at the <hi>Turcks Head</hi> in <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rn-hill,</hi> near the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39018:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39018:3"/>
            <head>To the Supream Authority, the <hi>Parliament</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <hi>Know you cannot be Ignorant of the (at preſent) Deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Eſtate of</hi> England, <hi>whoſe former Plenty, and Freedome, of Commerce, hath ſounded as Ecchoes of Tryumph to all Nations round about her: and in deſpite of envy or their Emulating her happineſs, made her Trade the Worlds</hi> Exchange: <hi>untill of late years (for ſuch is her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs) her Millions of plenty are grown to complaints, and ſuch her Commerce into a Languiſhing conſumption: ſo univerſally diſperſed that even the greateſt of her Gentry complain for want of Mony, whilſt their Tenants groan under the burthen of Contribution and Taxes; The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant and Mariner, too late ſorrowing for their loſs of no leſs then 1300 Sail of Ships ſince the Warr with</hi> Spain, whereof many richly laden; to the ruine of their Owners and Proprietors; when others yet Trading, and paying Exciſe, with other great Duties, complain more for the Intollerable burthen by the manner of Collecting it, then the duty it ſelf: the laws of Exciſe being in truth contrived (as if purpoſely) to mantain a numerous rabble of Exciſe-men, the moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and unprofitable members in a Common-wealth: who making themſelves gainers by the ruine of Trade, go away with the greateſt ſhare of the revennue, whilſt the private Souldier for want of pay is brought to a kind of beggarry; being driven to take upon truſt, (where they can have it,)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39018:4"/>
the very meat they eat; and conſidering their penni-worths to pay dear for the Intereſt. All which together with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of many, Thouſands poor Families diſtreſſed throughout the Nation, for want of Trade, being conſidered, I hope will ſo work upon your ſpirits, (now the Lord hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I preſume beyond your own Expectations brought you together) that you will not reſt till you have Improved this opportunity once more put into your hands of doing good for your Country, to which end you are called; wherein the Lord will undoubtedly own you, and thoſe yet unborn be Obliged to Honour your remembrance.</p>
            <p>And apprehending that amongſt other waighty affaires that of raiſing Monies for time to come, for ſupply of the Army, and Navy of the Common-wealth, by the moſt equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and propereſt waies, not burthenſome to the Nation, with the increaſe of Trade, Mony, and Shiping, (all ſo much wanting in <hi>England)</hi> are not the leaſt of Importance: and having had the peruſal of the ſeveral reports, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals made this <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Committee</hi> of Inſpection, with all others that have written in reference thereunto; I have upon ſerious conſideration ſubſtracted the moſt ſutable and (as I apprehend) propereſt collections from the whole, and have taken liberty to publiſh it, with ſome additions of my own obſervations in <hi>England,</hi> and Experience in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain parts: which, when receiving the Honour of your debate, will I hope merrit the favour of your good likeing, and the Authour have his expected reward, by being an Inſtrument of promoting the good and welfare of his Country.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S E.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39018:4"/>
            <head>The Toutch-ſtone of <hi>MONY</hi> and <hi>COMMERCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AMongſt the diverſity of Mettalls which God the Creator hath ſhut up in the concave Cloſet of the Earth; none is accounted more Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than Gold, and Silver; which ſince it became in uſe amongſt men may properly be termed the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall meaſure of all things, and the Staple of Commerce, which in All Ages, and Nations, where it goes drives the Wheel of Trade and Succeſs. I ſhall therefore (ſince the World gives it that Eſteem) begin with its Standard as in vallew here amongſt us.</p>
            <p>The Allay, or ſtandard of England (I mean the Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cical <note place="margin">The Engliſh Standard bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain.</note> vallew of Plate) being inferiour to none, if not the beſt and pureſt of <hi>Europe.</hi> and the large proportion in waight allowed to our pound <hi>Sterling,</hi> gives it the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vallue in Forrain parts, and is therefore by them the more covetted: ſo that its par or vallue runing higher in the North-Eaſt parts of the World then our Native Commodities; England is by that means made but the <hi>Carravan</hi> for its tranſportation from the South-Weſt parts thither; and by reaſon of the Warr with <hi>Spain,</hi> (a place that vended much of <hi>Engliſh</hi> manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures) together with the Obſtruction by us given, the <hi>Spaniſh Weſt-India-Fleet</hi> which occaſioned Plate to <note place="margin">Plate decreaſed and the reaſon why.</note> run at a higher vallue there; <hi>England</hi> hath of late years been prevented of Importing Plate as Formerly; and her exports thereof greater by reaſon of the loſs of her
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39018:5"/>
Southern Trade, from whence her Marchants uſually ſent Commodities for <hi>Holland</hi> and other Northern Countries of the production of Engliſh goods, which now are bought from the <hi>Dutch</hi> and others their Neighbours with Engliſh Coyn: who by that means are become almoſt Maſters, both of our Mony and Trade, which will prove of dangerous conſequence to England, if not timely prevented.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon of the Decreaſe of Plate, is by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance thereof melted down, and converted to the <note place="margin">Plate Melted down.</note> making of Silver and Gold Lace, Buttons, and the like, in which un-neceſſary ſuperfluity in the three Nations, of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> is waſted no leſs then two hundred Thouſand pounds <hi>Sterling</hi> Yearly, by a very good eſtimate of knowing perſons dealing therein.</p>
            <p>Alſo there is a great demunition of the Coyne of <hi>England,</hi> by converting it into Tankards, Bowls, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">By Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths.</note> Veſſels of Plate, which in a ſuper-abounding mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure we dayly ſee in <hi>Gold-Smiths Shops,</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Cittizens Houſes:</hi> far exceeding the Eſtates and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of moſt of them, which though convenient for private uſes, yet tends to the decreaſe of Monyes, and the Publique Stock of the Nation, and conſequently to the decay of Trade: which is contained in a propoſal late preſented the Committee of <hi>Safety</hi> by one Mr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> unto whom I give this remembrance, <note place="margin">Mr Marſhalls Propoſals.</note> though I know not the Author.</p>
            <p>And having I hope ſufficiently laid down the reaſons of the decreaſe, and exportation of <hi>Engliſh Coyn,</hi> which <note place="margin">Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver exported, how to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</note> is too apparent in the ſcarcety of Gold, but of late Years more frequently paſſing then Silver; and by the few half Crowns left in compariſon of the aboundance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39018:5"/>
Coyned ſince the Warr in <hi>England,</hi> (they being the moſt profitable to be exported, or melted down, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaſt worn, and waying more proportionably then ſmaler Coyn, from the Mint, by ſo much as the labour of Coynage is leſs:) I now propoſe the means for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe thereof, with advance to Trade and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Revennue.</p>
            <p>That from hence forward the <hi>Engliſh Shilling</hi> may <note place="margin">The Engliſh ſhillings to be made leſs.</note> contain in wait but <hi>11d,</hi> and the Silver to be a penny courſer; ſo that <hi>10d</hi> in vallue according to the preſent Standard may futurely be allowed taken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for <hi>12d Sterling,</hi> and ſo be Stamped; and the ſtandard fixed according to that vallue; all other Coyn runing alike in proportion.</p>
            <p>That the Mint in <hi>London,</hi> with others to be erected <note place="margin">The Mint to be ſet going, and all Mony new Coyned.</note> in the moſt proper places of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> may be ſet going; and all Monyes in the States hands above the vallue of groats (the ſmaler being worn and not conſiderable to return a profit,) may be forthwith new Coyned according to that ſtandard: and by degrees calling in the old Coyn and paying the owners again with new, (they allowing for all Clypt, and Broken,) all the Mony in <hi>England</hi> will (without obſtruction of Trade) be new Coyned into more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary peeces as ⅔ parts into half Crowns, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ⅓ into Shillings, and Six pences, whereof at preſent there is to great a proportion, as being the more troble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in counting; The <hi>Spaniard</hi> being ſo expert in this manner of new Coyning his Mony, that I have known all the Braſs Mony of his Kingdome (which cannot be leſs in number of peeces then 6 times the <hi>Sterling Mony</hi> in <hi>England,)</hi> new Coyned in two moneths time, which I here intimate to ſhew the facility
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39018:6"/>
of that, which ſome perhaps may think to be a work of great difficulty: But not approving of that cheat in <hi>Spain,</hi> I return to prevent the Cheats that ſome may alſo ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt will be practiſed in <hi>England,</hi> by falſe Coyning, <note place="margin">To pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vent cheats in falce Coynage.</note> though for my own part, I apprehend need not be feared.</p>
            <p>That it may be ordered upon ſome penalty that all Mony within <hi>London</hi> and lines of <hi>Communication</hi> may be brought into the <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> or ſome other ſafe place within the <hi>Citty:</hi> Or otherwiſe into ſome treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be appointed in every Pariſh; there to remain as in Banck until new Mony be given in Exchange: ſo that all ſums conſiderable (contracted for by Marchants or others) may be aſwell paid from one to another in Banck, as if actually told and delivered: the experience <note place="margin">Moni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to be brought into Bank.</note> whereof we find continueally practiſed in <hi>Holland, Genoway,</hi> and amongſt other Bankers, who find both eaſe and profit thereby; and I think would be alſo of great uſe in <hi>England,</hi> if here erected. And for all petty ſums for pocket uſe, it will preſently be ſupplyed by the Monyes firſt to be iſſued out of the Mint. The like manner of bringing their Monies into a Treaſury may be obſerved in other <hi>Citties</hi> and places of Commerce; and no Monies be ſuffered to paſs in payments but of the new Coyn Provided that any ſum of Monies paya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at a day certain by perſons either of Citty or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; if delivered into the next Bank or Treaſury; may be held paid, and Credit given for ſo much to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that of right ought to have it. And ſince I have hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at a Bank, I ſhall give the manner of it; I ſuppoſe not known to all perſons, but worth obſervation to ſome.</p>
            <p>A Bank is a Certain number of ſufficient men of Credit and Eſtates joyned together in a ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:39018:6"/>
for keeping ſeveral mens Caſh in one Treaſury; and <note place="margin">The nature of a Bank.</note> letting out imaginary Mony at Intereſt, for 2 ½, or 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> to Trades-men, or others that agree with them for the ſame: and making payment thereof by aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, paſſing each mans account from one to another; yet paying no monies: in ſo much, that if a Marchant or other perſon want Mony: If he have or can but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure credit in Bank, he may make as good payment by aſſignment in Bank without it. As for Example, the ſaid Marchant buyes Cloath of a Cloathier for 100 <hi>lb.</hi> value more or leſs, and goes with him to the Bank, where he is debtor for ſo much monies as he takes up; and the Clothier is made Creditor for ſo much as he ſold his goods for to the ſaid Marchant: Then ſuch Clothier having occaſion to pay Mony to a Stapler or Wool-monger for Wool bought, the ſaid Clothier is made Debtor, and the Wool-monger Creditor upon account: the ſaid Wool-monger buys Wool of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Farmer, for ſo much Mony, more or leſs; ſo the Wool-monger is made Debtor, and the Farmer Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: the Farmer muſt pay Rent to his Landlord, and is likewiſe made Debtor, and his Landlord Creditor: the ſaid Landlord for his occaſions buys good of a Mercer, Grocer, Vintner, or the like, or from all; then he is made Debtor, and ſuch Mercer or other Trades-man Creditor: then peradventure ſuch Mercer or other Trads-man buyes goods from the ſame Marchants that took up the firſt Credit in Bank, and ſtands yet Debtor there, but upon ſale of his goods to the Mercer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trads-man both clears their accounts in Bank: and ſo in all Trads; as occaſion preſents, which is practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in many places as aforeſaid, and is of very great uſe and advantadge to Trade; the payment made therein
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39018:7"/>
being generally eſteemed better by ½ <hi>per Cent.</hi> then out of Bank, as preventing troble and the receiving Clipt or bad Mony: but being already publiſhed at large in <note place="margin">Mr <hi>Lambs</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:</note> a Book writen by Mr. <hi>Lamb,</hi> who is worthy of incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement therein: I ſhall not ſtay longer hereon, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to my purpoſe.</p>
            <p>That to prevent the melting down of any Coyn, by <hi>Gold-Smiths</hi> or others, to the prejudice of the State and <note place="margin">To prevent the melting down of Plate.</note> decreaſe of Monies: An Impoſſition of <hi>12d</hi> upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ounce of Silver, and the like proportionably upon Gold, may be laid upon all Plate already wrought, and to be wrought into any form for uſe, other then the Mint, aſwell in the hands of <hi>Gold-Smiths</hi> as other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever: and an Office to be appointed in <hi>London,</hi> and each reſpective County of <hi>England</hi> for the ſame to be paid, upon penalty of forfeiture: and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in teſtimony thereof ſome ſtamp of the Office, and accordingly to be regeſtred. Alwaies provided, that ſuch as will bring in wrought Plate to the Mint, may be allowed to Coyn it upon like terms as at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>That all Gold may be Coyned alike in proportion, <note place="margin">New Coynage of Gold.</note> regard being had to its current value, which now runs higher then Silver by <hi>2ſh</hi> in the pound: ſo that out of every <hi>20ſh</hi> peece of Gold will be taken the waight of <hi>5ſh 4d.</hi> to make its parrity or quallity equal with that Standard.</p>
            <p>That the ſuperfluous wearing of Silver, and Gold Lace, Buttons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be prevented by good <note place="margin">To prevent the waring of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Lace.</note> example given of ſome other more comly Trimming to be worn at Court; or by adirect prohibition againſt it, as is at preſent in <hi>France:</hi> Or otherwiſe by laying an Impoſition of <hi>1ſh 6d</hi> on the ounce to be paid by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39018:7"/>
maker thereof; or by laying a yearly Fine or duty on the perſons wearing it, of the quallity of an Eſq; or upwards <hi>10l.</hi> each: the Gentleman <hi>5l.</hi> and all of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaner quallity <hi>3l. per Annum</hi> each: which I preſume will bring in a Conſiderable revennue, or elſe cauſe the ſame to be held contemptible and not worn: either of which will prove uſefull to the Publique good, and prevent ſuch ſuperfluous extravigancies.</p>
            <p>Which being done, I doubt not but in a ſhort time <note place="margin">Of the increaſe of Mony, and Trade.</note> the want and ſcarcety both of Gold and Silver, will be found ſo plentifull in <hi>England,</hi> that our loſt Trade will again revive; and no Commodity be held the dearer for this moderate advance of Monies; which is not here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced to incourage the Supream Authority of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to Immitate our Neighbours the <hi>Hollander,</hi> and other States and Princes, whoſe uſuall cuſtome is to advance their Monies in their payments, and to decry them in their receipts; which though ſome account to be good State Pollicy, yet I am bold to call it great <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The manner of Inhancing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> oppreſſion, when no excuſe can be pleaded other then State Intereſt; but otherwiſe, if in pollicy, done either to keep a Competency, or to ſupply a ſcarcity of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in a Kingdome or Common-wealth. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, if the State of <hi>England</hi> had put the <hi>20ſh.</hi> peece of Gold higher in value but <hi>6d.</hi> when it firſt began to riſe it ſelf; and be drawn away it would have ſtopt that currant, and perhaps alſo have prevented Forrain Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of covetting our Silver, by keeping them Ignorant of its worth and value; and I wiſh heartily that ſuch <note place="margin">That the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Gold, and Silver might have been better p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> timely care were taken in the preventing other Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of as great Conſequence by inſpecting the proceedings of Forrain Princes, and States, touching Trade and Commerce, (wherein we are as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39018:8"/>
as any,) that we might not ſuffer our ſelves to be out-witted, and by degrees Courted out of all Trade, as we have from our Gold and Silver, for which the gapp being now opened ſo wide, and the ſcarcity of Gold by degrees riſing a diſparrity from its ſtanding value, to above <hi>2s.</hi> in every <hi>20s.</hi> and our Silver by being here (as I may properly ſay) bought at ſo low a rate, is found a better Commodity in Forrain parts than our Native Manufacture, and Commodities: ſo that the ſtream is even grown to an inundation and drowning of all Trade, for want of ſuch timely prevention.</p>
            <p>And truly I apply this my deſign of advancing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies more principally, as a means to reconcile the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <note place="margin">This deſign is more to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the value of Mony and Trade, then for a Revennue.</note> diſparrity of the Coyn and Trade of <hi>England,</hi> with the currant Commerce, of Forrain parts, then ſingly to advance the States revenue; though I confeſs, finding the ſame will prove ſo advantagious both to State and Common good, I am the more incouraged hereunto, and am glad to be ſerviceable to both; conceiving the States advantage thereby cannot be leſs then 5 Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <note place="margin">The benefit to the State, and Common-wealth.</note> beſides the eaſe to the Common-wealth, of paying the like ſum in contribution, and other Taxes; and no man have the leſs in eſteem or vallue, but all will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched again by Trade, that will revive by the return of Treaſure; which the <hi>Dutch</hi> having more plentifull in reallity then <hi>England:</hi> beſides being ſupplyed imaginary, upon occaſion by the help of their Banks, is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal reaſon they eat us out of Trade, and by no better way then this to be prevented. Then will all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Traders have vent for their Commodities, and the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer have Mony to pay his Landlord; Cloathing and other Manufacturies will find a market, and be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged: the Souldier have his pay, and the Common-wealth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39018:8"/>
in general again have Trade, all being now at a ſtand for want of Mony the Uſurer only excepted, whoſe ungodly gain is become the greater: So that if it ſhould be admitted, the ſcope of this deſigne were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no other account but to ſatisfy the Immergencies of State. (which I hope I have given ſufficient reaſons of Contradiction) it cannot be more juſtly and equitably impoſed then upon the greateſt Mony-mongers, who <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs have born the leaſt ſhare of Taxes.</note> of all Men have born the leaſt Share of Burthen in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> during the late Wars, and juſtly deſerves this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
            <p>And referring the ingenious States man, that deſires to enquire farther into the miſtery and practice of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain States concerning riſing and falling their monies to the ſeveral and differing Authors that have written more at large thereupon; I conclude this ſubject, with this my obſervation, That whilſt we put ſo high an eſteem upon Forraign goods, and continue our Coyn <note place="margin">The reaſon why Plate is drawn away.</note> at the ſame vallue, it will be ſtill drawn away, and our Exports become the leſs; which is wholly Inconſiſtant with the Common-good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>England;</hi> whoſe poor are imployed, Trade increaſed, and wealth brought in by ſo much the more, as the current of her Exports ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed her Imports: which ſtream hath run backward ever ſince the <hi>Spaniſh War:</hi> which War more duly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the dayly remembrance of the Supream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>England;</hi> then <hi>Callis</hi> did to the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> whileſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t continued under the <hi>Engliſh Scepter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having done with the ſubject of Mony: I come <note place="margin">Of Shiping and Commerce.</note> now to ſpeak of Commerce and Shipping, the other Wheel of Trade, Driven by <hi>Marchants;</hi> but ſo laden with Impoſitions, and more by the abuſes in col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39018:9"/>
it, as if <hi>Marchants</hi> (the moſt honourable profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and principal Fountain, from whoſe Induſtrious ſtreams floweth in the riches of a Common-wealth) were guilty of ſome high crimination, and not deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the leaſt incouragement. And ſince I have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted the principal parts of this compoſure from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authors whom I deſire not to rob of the thanks due unto them for ſo Publique a merrit; I have and ſhall give each a due remembrance, and come now to <hi>Mr Hawkins,</hi> the ſubſtance of whoſe Propoſal made <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr</hi> Hawkins <hi>his Propoſal touching Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</hi>
               </note> to this <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Committee</hi> of Inſpection, was for the taking away of Contribution, with Cuſtome and Exciſe upon all goods Imported or Exported in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh bottoms:</hi> and that in conſideration thereof, and for a Revennue to the State, an Impoſition ſhould be laid only upon <hi>Wine, Beer,</hi> and <hi>Tobaccho,</hi> throughout <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> to be Collected by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, to be appointed in every County, in manner following.</p>
            <p>That every <hi>Vintner, Strong-water-ſeller, Inn-keeper, Ale houſe,</hi> and <hi>Coffee-ſeller,</hi> in the three Nations ſhould yearly compound for his drauft of any ſuch Liquors and Drinks: and to pay quarterly the ſum to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with the ſaid Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>That all private Families whatſoever ſhould pay yearly for the Drink ſpent in their Houſes, according to the rates and qualifications following.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>All Gentlemen of <hi>1000lb. per Annum,</hi> or upwards, or <hi>10000lb.</hi> perſonal Eſtate; or a <hi>Marchant</hi> for themſelves, and all in their Families <hi>per Head.</hi> 8 or <hi>10s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:39018:9"/>
                  <item>All others of <hi>500lb. per Annum,</hi> or upwards, or <hi>5000lb</hi> perſonal Eſtate, to pay for all in their Families <hi>per Head.</hi> 6 or <hi>8s</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All thoſe of <hi>100lb per Annum,</hi> or <hi>500lb</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Eſtate, to pay for themſelves and all in their Families <hi>per Head.</hi> 4 or <hi>6s</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All worth <hi>100lb,</hi> and thoſe in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to pay <hi>per Head.</hi> 2 or <hi>4s</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All worth <hi>20lb</hi> Eſtate, and their Families, excepting all Children under, 12 years of age to pay <hi>per Head.</hi> 0 or <hi>1s</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And all Perſons of a lower Eſtate to go free.</p>
            <p>That all perſons that take <hi>Tobaccho</hi> by the Pipe, ſneezing, or Chewing, to pay yearly as follow.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>All Lords and perſons of Dignity, and their Ladies to pay yearly each. <hi>3l</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Knights and their Ladies, each. <hi>2l</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Eſquiers and their Wives, each. <hi>1l</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gentlemen and their Wives, each. <hi>10s</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Yoewmen and their Wives, each. <hi>5s</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Handicraft men and their Wives, each. <hi>2s</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Labourours and their Wives, each. <hi>1s</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All Servants and Children above 12 years, old. <hi>1s</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Calculation made of the Revennue that will be brought in by the Publique draft of <hi>Wine, Beer,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Drinks in the three Nations, is a Million yearly.</p>
            <p>By the rates ſet upon all private Families, for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and thoſe they have in Family, is computed will amount yearly to two Millions.</p>
            <p>Beſides, for the Takers of <hi>Tobaccho,</hi> which is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain till ſetled, and therefore not eſtimated. Which ſum of three Millions is more then was ever yet Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39018:10"/>
by Cuſtome, Exciſe, and Contribution: beſides by taking off the burthen from Trade, Mony, and Shiping, which are the ſtay and ſupport of Commerce, will be again increaſed in England.</p>
            <p>This propoſal receiving the debate of <hi>Parliament</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The reſult of the Committee of Inſpection thereupon.</note> was committed to the <hi>Committe</hi> of <hi>Inſpection:</hi> and upon their conſideration confined only to the Publique draft and ſale of <hi>Wine, Beer,</hi> and <hi>Tobaccho,</hi> in publique Shops, and Houſes: whereby I perceive they were not pleaſed to approve of any ſuch Impoſition to be laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on private Families: Remembring (as I ſuppoſe) how diſtaſtfull it was in the year 1651. when Exciſe was paid by private Families, much after this manner. Neither do I thing it proper at preſent, conſidering how the State of affairs ſtand in England, to take off the Duty of Cuſtome and Exciſe from a few <hi>Marchants</hi> that ſell it again for profit, and place it ſo generall upon all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Families, now not ſenſible of paying any thing; though in truth I hartily wiſh it gone from all, except from ſuch goods as in pollicy ought to pay a greater duty then ordinary; for incouragement and ſetting a ballance to Trade. But for taking away the troble oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned to <hi>Marchants</hi> by the ill method or manner of Collecting it, which is ſo great a Charge to the Publique; that I think it moſt neceſſary to be forth-with done; which will be a moſt acceptable ſervice and favour to <hi>Marchants.</hi> And for that I find it ſo rationally anſwered in a paper put in before the ſaid Committee by <hi>Mr. Cradock</hi> (whoſe report alſo touching this ſubject, lies before them) I think it propper to commit the heads thereof, alſo to publique view.</p>
            <p>Its therein confeſſed, that the taking away of all Cuſtome, and Exciſe, lying for the moſt part upon For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39018:10"/>
goods, will increaſe a Forrain Trade, and make <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Cradocks <hi>anſwer to Mr.</hi> Hawkins <hi>his Propoſals.</hi>
               </note> the Importation and Conſumption of <hi>England</hi> to be the greater: But mony and a great part of the Engliſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures will by that means fall and decreaſe; for that by laying a duty upon ſuch Forrain manufactures whereof the like are made in England, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueing of it upon Coals, Lead, and Tynn, not to be had elſe-where but in England, doth not only bring Forrain Nations to contribute to our Revennue, but ſupports our Native Induſtry, which otherwiſe would be under ſould and diſcouraged: and if not by that means ballanced and ſupported with ſome more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per law made to prevent the Exportation of Wools, and Fullers-earth, whereby the Native Commodities of England exported may be made equivolent in vallue to purchaſe the Commodities Imported, and Conſumed; It muſt neceſſarily follow that Plate muſt go to ſupply it, as it hath done for ſome years paſt. Moreover it were moſt Imprudent for this Common-wealth, not to have regard to the Incouragement of Trade with Friends, and Alyes, and with that Country which vends moſt of our ſuperfluities, and ſupplies our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: and otherwiſe to diſcourage that Trade which hinders our manufacturies at home, or proves otherwiſe prejudicial to our Plantations abroad; which will never be well inſpected without a Committee of Trade. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the method in Collecting the Cuſtome and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, may be ſo amended that by taking away the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous number of Officers, and preventing the frauds of ſome <hi>Marchants</hi> that by ſaving their own duties are inabled to under-ſell their Neighbours, to the great prejudice of Trade, that the revenue may be brought in by a more proper way for incouragement of Trade, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39018:11"/>
eaſe of ſo great a charge to the Nation.</p>
            <p>Which if once taken into Conſideration, <hi>M. Hawkins</hi> his method would be found aſmuch ſhort in proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as his Calculation of ſo many Millions is too large in quantity: for allowing the 9725. Pariſhes in England to have 160. Families, in each Pariſh, at 6 Perſons in a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; the whole number of Perſons makes 9336000. which being reaſonably proportioned according to the rates ſet upon private Families, will not amount to the part of Two Millions, the ſum eſtimated; and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> above ½ aſmuch, they both paying in Cuſtome and Exciſe, not the ⅛ part, nor in <hi>Contribution</hi> more then the ⅓ part, were as unequall as impoſſible in thoſe parts to be Collected.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the Calculation of the Publique ſale of Wine, and Beer, the miſtake cannot be leſs: for if the late Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers by ſo much complained of Extortion, could not make their Rents contracted for their reſpective-Farms of Beer and Ale in England, which together with the whole receipts of Cuſtome and Exciſe upon Wines in the three Nations (which paies as much as it firſt Coſt,) amounts unto in all but <hi>420000lb per Annum;</hi> How can <hi>Mr. Hawkins</hi> expect to raiſe a Million upon the ſame, And admitting the Vintner may be compounded with at a Rate conſiderable; the <hi>Marchant</hi> being freed from paying Cuſtome and Exciſe may drink Wine in his own houſe at half the Tavern price; As other private Families may alſo, that buy it from <hi>Marchants;</hi> which will not eaſily be prevented: ſo that the Vintner and that revennue will infallibly be ruined.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Tobaccho Mr. Cradock</hi> agrees with <hi>Mr. Hawkins,</hi> that the receipt will be uncertain till ſetled and approves of the conceipt to be good, though not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39018:11"/>
for the end Intended; for that the laying ſuch an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition thereupon will peradventure cauſe many Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman and others to leave it for Fancie, as they took it: and the Ladies of England that now take it too publique to do it more private, not to the diſhonour of their Sex and Country.</p>
            <p>I have the rather been large upon this Propoſal, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it took up ſo long Debate before this <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Inſpection,</hi> and was taking with many of them. For I confeſs if ſo great a Revennue could be made out, and the People be brought to pay it willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch a method may be drawn from <hi>Mr. Hawkins</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry whether it be beſt for Wine and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baccho to pay by Lycence?</note> his propoſals as may be good for advance of Trade. But what the <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Inſpection</hi> hath done in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning <hi>Wines</hi> and <hi>Tobacchoes</hi> to pay by Lycence, I may not civilly contradict: yet am bold to Query; Whether that duty will be as properly collected from many hands, ſo diſperſed throughout the Nations, as from the Few Imports thereof? And if it be by any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that it will much advance the revennue (which I fear will not prove ſo,) Whether it may not alſo be called hard meaſure when the Sellers thereof are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to pay ſuch a duty, or leave off Trading in thoſe Commodities, for which they have no warrant to rate the ſame in the <hi>Wines,</hi> and <hi>Tobacchoes,</hi> to be ſold by any method or preſcription, other then every mans fancie: it being otherwiſe (at preſent) in the Brewers Trade, who makes his Drink ſo much the ſmaller, according to an exact proportion of ſo much the Barrel as is laid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon?</p>
            <p>But for Beer, Ale <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Publique houſes, it will be <note place="margin">Beer and Ale, will be beſt col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe.</note> undoubtedly the propereſt way of Collecting it by Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, as <hi>Mr Hawkins</hi> hath deſigned, whereby the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39018:12"/>
Commonwealth will be excuſed of <hi>20000lb per Annum,</hi> now paid in Sallaries to Officers, beſides brybes, and the trouble of attendance upon Offices, to make weekly entries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>10ſh.</hi> yearly paid for every Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to the <hi>Juſtices of Peace,</hi> their Clarks by the perſons that ſell Drink in Lycenſed houſes, will ſerve to pay half the rent of many of the poorer ſort. But for that I find it moſt plainly ſet down in the report made by <hi>Mr Cradock,</hi> part in Print (but never publiſhed,) and part written, I have inſerted it in the latter part of my Book <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Touching a method pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in, by Mr</hi> Cradock, <hi>to the</hi> Parliament</note> 
               <hi>Verbatim;</hi> and alſo taken from thence the cheifeſt part of my Method, (touching Cuſtome, and Forrain Exciſe, with the increaſe of Shiping,) the rather for that I find his method ſo well approved by many Members of <hi>Parliament, Collonel Harvy</hi> eſpecially, whoſe experience in thoſe affaires, I render inferiour to none; I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proceed as follows.</p>
            <p>That the Book of rates for Cuſtoms may be referred to ſome fit Perſon experienced in Trade, to be rectified; <note place="margin">Of Cuſtomes and Books of Rates.</note> and all Goods and Marchandize rated therein accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the true worth and vallue now Currant.</p>
            <p>That where regard ſhall be had to Impoſe a greater or ſmaler duty to be paid upon any Commodity either for advance to the revennue, the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſervation of our own Trade, or to diſcourage or invite others to Trade with us, in general or particular Commodities; it may be done by impoſing more or leſs to be paid in the pound, according to ſuch Book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Rates, and not by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a differing price upon Goods of the ſame ſpecie and vallue; as is improperly done in the Book of Rates now in being and cannot be properly corrected in any part, without a new Impreſſion of the whole.</p>
            <p>That the duty may bepaid upon all Goods alike, by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39018:12"/>
all Perſons, the difference to be only upon Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <note place="margin">Forrain Ships only to pay Forrain duties.</note> Imported or Exported in Forrain Bottoms; (that is to ſay) ſuch Ship or Veſſel not built in England, or Engliſh Teritories, or not in the poſſeſſion of Engliſh Owners, and whereof the Maſter and ¾ of the Marriners are not Natural born Subjects of England: That ſuch goodsand no other ſhall pay a greater duty in the nature of Forrain Cuſtome, which will be of greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the State, be more agreeable with the gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Common-wealth, and prove the beſt expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for increaſe of Shipping, and incouragement of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>London, Briſtol, Plimouth, Dover, Portſmouth, Hull</hi> and <hi>Yarmouth</hi> may be made free Ports for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of making free Ports in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> to Import, Land, and Houſe all dry goods in the States Ware-Houſes, without paying any duty, more then a reaſonable rate for Ware-Houſe room: and that ſuch goods, with all other Forrain goods whatſoever, may be at pleaſure exported in ſuch Engliſh Ships as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; with all Cuſtome and Exciſe paid, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned; and in Forrain bottoms with half ſubſidy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, as at preſent: whereby goods may find a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket in Forrain parts to ſome advadtage. The State hereby cannot hazzard more then <hi>19000lb per Annum</hi> now received for half ſubſidy, which I am confident will return with great advance, when that Clog of Trade is Taken away, which only prevents goods here to be Imported: for Exportation, as in <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Legorn,</hi> where moſt goods conſumed or ſent by land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage up into the Country pays a greater Exciſe then in England: beſides Engliſh Shipping will be Imployed in Exportation of great quantities of Forrain goods, yearly, that will then be laid on ſhoar by <hi>Sweds, Danes,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39018:13"/>
Hamburgars,</hi> and other of the <hi>Eaſt-Land Frozen Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries;</hi> whoſe Shiping comming home but little to late, are inforced to remain in our Harbours for ſafety moſt <note place="margin">England <hi>as free as</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> part of the Winter; during which time they might make another Voyage to the <hi>South-Weſt parts,</hi> and return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain Laden: ſo that excepting what is done in favour to Engliſh Shiping, which cannot ſafely be taken away, England will be as free as <hi>Holland,</hi> or any Port in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Timber may be Prohibited to be Exporred, and care taken for its preſervation: For the <hi>Hollander</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>For building of Shiping in</hi> England.</note> (though buying his Timber from us, and other Forrain parts) makes Shiping his great manufacture; whileſt the Engliſh having it more plentifull both in <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>New-England,</hi> inſtead of building one, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently buy four Ships from them, which will be prevented by putting this difference between Engliſh and Forrain bottoms, and will be ſo great an Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for building here, that in few years Shiping may become as great a manufacture in England, to her ſupport againſt Forrain Enemies, and encreaſe both of Trade and the Revennue.</p>
            <p>That to the end all Forrainers may be prevented of entring Ships for Engliſh, whoſe Proprietors, and building are not really ſuch, all Shiping now belonging to the reſpective Ports and Harbours of England may be ordered forth-with to be regiſtred, and a duty of <hi>40ſh. per Tunn:</hi> laid upon all that ſhall be bought for the Future, from Forrain Nations, to be regeſtred alſo in like manner; and oath being made by the owners, or the major part of them, before the Commiſſioners or Collectors of the Cuſtome houſe appointed for the Port, of each Ship really and truly appertaining to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39018:13"/>
Engliſh proprietors, Certifficate thereof ſhall be given, under their hands and ſeal of Office; which with the uſuall oath at preſent made by Maſters upon entry in Cuſtome houſe, may be a ſufficient teſtimony in any Port of England; and all other Ships be deemed as For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain, and the duty be Collected for all goods Imported or Exported therein accordingly.</p>
            <p>That to prevent the Exportation of <hi>Wools,</hi> and <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-Earth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">To prevent the Exportation of Wools and Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-Earth.</note> it may be made Fellony for any perſon proved to be ayding, conſenting to, or aſſiſting in the Shiping or putting the ſame on board any Forrain Ship, or Veſſell, or Engliſh Ship of War, (or ſome of them by report uſing to carry it for <hi>Holland,</hi> being never viſited the Cuſtom-houſe Officers,) and that the Captain, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and Mariners thereof (if within ſeven years after ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in England,) may be alſo adjudged as Fellons: But if Shiped in other Engliſh bottoms, the Goods, and Ship, only to be forfeited: for that few Maſters (if any at all) offend in that kind without approbation of their own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who are too often conſenting to, and Imployers of Maſters and their Sea-men upon that account: ſo that by taking away the penalty from Maſters and Mariners, (at preſent lying ſo hard that I conceive it duls the edge of the Law) their Teſtimony, which is all that can be had, will not only be preſerved, but Juſtice be more freely Executed. And if Wools were Prohibited to be water born, within the <hi>Dominions</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon any pretence whatſoever, (except to be brought from an Iſland to the Main) and alſo not to be put in any Houſe, Barn, or other place nearer the Sea or any Navigable River then the owners dwelling-Houſe, upon pain of Confiſcation, with a greater fine, according to the nature of the Offence, I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39018:14"/>
it would prevent much fraud practiſed; which is of very great Importance to England, and moſt worthy of remedy.</p>
            <p>That upon ſeizing any Ship or other goods: whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver upon pretence of breach of any law, or for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment <note place="margin">Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes to have more power.</note> of Duty, the Commiſſioners of the Cuſtomes in <hi>London</hi> may be Impowred to call any perſon before them, and to take examinations upon oath touching the ſame; and if they ſee cauſe to diſcharge ſuch ſeizure; (referring only ſuch as they find in their judgement duly ſeized into the <hi>Exchequer,)</hi> and that the difficult proofe now lying upon the ſeizor (which I doubt introduces <note place="margin">The proofe to ly upon the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of goods ſeizen.</note> much perjury) may be put upon the proprietor; who if innocent of Fraud intended, is the beſt able to clear his goods without further expence or delay by ſute in the <hi>Exchequer:</hi> beſides much fraud in ſaving Cuſtomes, will by this means be prevented: Provided it may not be conſtrued to extend any power to Officers of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes for ſeizing other goods but ſuch as by very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable or apparent demonſtration are in truth ſeizable, whereof the Commiſſiones of the Cuſtomes, may take care for preſervation of Trade, and puniſhing offenders according to their demerrits.</p>
            <p>This being the ſubſtance of what I apprehend is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient touching the premiſes, and neceſſary to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to whom I have preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to Dedicate theſe my unworthy lines, Concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it within the power of the Commiſſioners of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes to rectify other things amiſs; in the method whereof more is ſpoken in Mr <hi>Cradocks</hi> report; unto which I refer my ſelf and others, deſirous of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, and proceed to the method for Exciſe.</p>
            <p>That the ſame Book of Rates to be made for Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39018:14"/>
may alſo ſtand and be for Exciſe; the difference <note place="margin">Method for Exciſe.</note> of paying more or leſs then Cuſtome to be rated ſo much more or leſs in the pound, in like manner as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: which will prove a kind of check to each Office, by the other, and be the beſt Informant to the general Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyours that ſhall be appointed over both.</p>
            <p>That the Exciſe and Cuſtomes being dependent one <note place="margin">Exciſe to be brought to the Cuſtome-houſe.</note> upon the other, may be reduced into one Intire Office, (the receipts only to be kept diſtinct,) and mannaged by the ſame Commiſſioners and Officers; which will be very much to the eaſe and accommodation of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> in their diſpatches, and take off the trouble from Shop-keepers and others of fetching tickets, (which is the cheef cauſe of ſuch complaint againſt the duty.</p>
            <p>That in order thereunto, inſtead of the firſt buyer <note place="margin">Marchants to pay Exciſe.</note> the <hi>Marchant</hi> may be made lyable to pay the Exciſe; who doth the ſame voluntary already, in all the out parts, and many alſo in <hi>London</hi> ſelling their goods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p>That in lew of the <hi>Marchants</hi> ſtanding lyable to pay, <note place="margin">Time to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Exciſe, ſix moneths time may be given him to pay for the like quantity he entred in-wards, and paid Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, regard being had to ſuch Commodities as are not ſold or exported within the ſaid term, which may have three moneths time more, but no longer. Alſo that a certain allowance may be computed for <hi>Leakage</hi> of Wines, and other liquid or waſting Commodities, at ſo much <hi>per Cent,</hi> and no other allowance to be made upon any pretence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>That by making that a ſtanding Law, which is now <note place="margin">Marchants wil have warrant to ſell the duty with his goods.</note> ſo differently practiſed, and falls out often as Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies between the <hi>Marchant</hi> and firſt buyer, who although by the Law in being) is lyable to pay the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39018:15"/>
yet the <hi>Marchant</hi> alſo ſtands obliged to ſee it done, and diſcharged upon his account (which trouble is in ſmal parcels of goods ſold a greater inconvenience then the payment of the duty) many ſutes will be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by prevented, and the <hi>Marchant</hi> have more poſſitive warrant to demand for and ſell both the Cuſtome and Exciſe with his goods.</p>
            <p>That all Collectors and Receivers of Cuſtomes their <note place="margin">Accounts how to be kept.</note> Journal or day Book, of receipts may ſerve to charge the <hi>Merchant</hi> for Exciſe, whoſe Firm may alſo ſerve for Bill of Entry at Cuſtome-Houſe, and from thence be transferred to the Leagar, (which is all the trouble extraordinary,) and both accounts are compleated: the trouble in this and all things elſe, will be to both <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant</hi> and <hi>Officer</hi> ſhortned, the accounts upon occaſion readier to be compared and examined, and many miſtakes and other inconveniences that now happen between both, be prevented.</p>
            <p>That the 5 <hi>per Cent</hi> now allowed upon all Goods en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <note place="margin">5 per Cent <hi>to be allowed.</hi>
               </note> in Cuſtome-Houſe may be taken off, and in lew thereof 5 <hi>per Cent</hi> may be allowed the <hi>Marchant</hi> in Monies, upon payment of his Exciſe: Provided it be paid in at the day appointed, as aforeſaid: otherwiſe the <hi>Marchant</hi> ſhall not claim any benefit thereof: whereby Arrears will be prevented, by which the State hath lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> many hundred thouſand pounds.</p>
            <p>That the Officers of Cuſtomes and Exciſe, are ſo far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> from correſponding one with the other, or the one to <note place="margin">The Officers of Exciſe and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, help to cheat the ſtate.</note> queſtion that which might prevent a fraud to the other Office, (if it bring no profit to himſelf, as ſervants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one Maſter ſhould do,) that they are rather helpfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cheat the State againſt each others Office, as thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſervants of two different Intereſt; which ſhews ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:39018:15"/>
unneceſſary and Inconſiſtant one of them ſtands with the Publique good.</p>
            <p>That ſeven Commiſſioners may be appointed at the <note place="margin">The number of Commiſſioners.</note> Cuſtome-Houſe to mannage both duties; whether the Exciſe may be removed in all Ports: and that any three of the ſaid Commiſſioners may be a <hi>Corum;</hi> ſo that they may divide into two Committees upon occaſion: and that 8 hours in the Day may be allowed for all men to have their buſineſs done, either in Cuſtome or Exciſe, (that is to ſay, from 8 in the morning till 12 a Clock, and from 2 till 6 in the afternoon.) And that all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Officers may be diſcharged, excepting ſome few Accountants, and Surveyours, which will be inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in reſpect of the preſent number which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Method will be uſeleſs.</p>
            <p>That the prejudice to the State for want of redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <note place="margin">Exciſe makes leſs then Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</note> the Exciſe ſooner to a more certain method is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, in that the ſaid Duties of Exciſe, ſet on Wines and many other Commodities is double as much (and in no particular leſs then the duty of Cuſtomes; yet as to the ſame Commodities, it ever came ſhort in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of what the Cuſtomes yeeldeth to the Revenue, as may appear by the account following, taken out of Mr <hi>Cradocks</hi> report: which I have examined by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors Books, and do think it worthy to be hear Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The totall receipts of the Cuſtomes of England are</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr</hi> Cradocks <hi>account.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>uſually</hi> 390000l. per Annum, <hi>as it amounted unto, for the laſt four years, taking them together; from which I ſubſtract</hi> 95000l. per Annum, <hi>received for Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive goods Exported, and</hi> 19000l. per Annum, <hi>for half ſubſidy of Forrain goods again Exported, and the real receipt of Forrain goods conſumed in England is Yearly.</hi> 276000l.</item>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:39018:16"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That the ſaid Forrain goods conſumed ought to pay Exciſe: which upon Wines, Drugs, and many other Commodities is double as much as the duty of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and upon all other Commodities</hi> 5 per Cent, <hi>more; ſo that the Exciſe may be reaſonably computed at leaſt ¼ part more then Cuſtome, which then amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to</hi> 345000l. per Annum, <hi>from which is deducted for Leakage of Wines, and other Liquid Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties after Houſing</hi> 8000l. per Annum, <hi>which is all that can be pretended, and the real receipt of Exciſe Yearly ought to be.</hi> 337000l.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For the Exciſe of Forrain goods, for the laſt four years paſt by a Computed medium for one year have been received but.</hi> 175000l.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>So there appears to be loſt in the Collecting it (by the preſent method) of what it ought to make accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the entries in Cuſtome-Houſe, Yearly.</hi> 162000l.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Moreover there may be preſerved by bringing the Exciſe under the Cuſtome-Houſe management, and taking away the ſuperſtuous number of Officers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſident charges, Yearly.</hi> 030000l.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alſo by puting the Exciſe of Beer, and Ale, into the method following, to be paid by Lycence in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Counties of England</hi> (London <hi>excepted) it may be Collected for</hi> 6d <hi>in the pound better then for the 2ſh at preſent allowed the Sub-commiſſioners; and thereby, will be alſo preſerved Yearly.</hi> 018000l.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>So the demunition of the Revennue by the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous charge of Exciſe Officers and apparent loſs (as I conceive by the improper method) in collecting it is Yearly 210000 pounds (allowing the Cuſtome receipts the ſame, which by a better method might be alſo very much improved) I ſay.</hi> 210000l.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I preſume ſome that are acquainted with the receipts <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exciſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Manron.</note> of the Exciſe may alledge that a greater ſum then <hi>175000l,</hi> was received for Forrain Goods the laſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39018:16"/>
Years which is confeſſed; but Computing the laſt four Years (which is the propereſt way to find its reall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come) and it will be found not to exceed the ſaid ſum: yet I confeſs a very great Improvement was the laſt year made by regulating their Method, in keeping Marchants accounts, which was done by <hi>Major Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> one of the late Commiſſioners, whoſe ingenuity duly obſerves this remembrance.</p>
            <p>I confeſs my own opinion could not credit this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, with other particulars in Mr <hi>Cradocks</hi> report, (as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cuſtome falen ſince</hi> 1655.</note> the revenue of Cuſtomes to be decreaſed 80000 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> ſince the Year 1655. finding the totall receipts as great as formerly) untill I was convinced of its reallity by a further inſpection into the Book of Rates, as I have likewiſe made into the method of Exciſe, which I find contrived as if purpoſely deſigned to ruine Trade; by compelling every perſon buying or ſelling any Goods in the ſtrickneſs of the Law to fetch a Ticket before it be delivered (though living at never ſo remote a diſtance from the Exciſe Office) or elſe muſt ſubmit his Goods and himſelf and Trade to be <note place="margin">Trouble to Marchants by the ill method and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences.</note> interupted by every (of the too many) Exciſe Officers, which is not all; for he that deſires to walk according to their Exciſe rule, is ſo much enſlaved by the long and tedious attendance upon Offices, that, beſides his own trouble and hinderance in his Trade, requires a Servants labour extraordinary to all of any conſiderable dealings. And I am bold to affirm that the very Officers of Exciſe are as chargable to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as a conſiderable Army: Beſides, the preſent method refers ſo much to the Oaths of all Trades and their ſervants that he is become the moſt expert Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant that ſweares with the moſt handſome reſervations,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39018:17"/>
and knows beſt how to equivocate: which cuſtome of ſinning hath ſo taken away the Conſcience of it, that by ſuch careleſs ſwearing is introduced moſt wilfull perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; to the great diſhonour of God the ſcandal of our religion, and infamy of this Nation: ſo that if not ſpeedily ſtopped, it will eat out the very life of Grace, and Spirit of Fidelity from amongſt us: whereby that ſacred bond of an Oath (obſerved by the very <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> as the moſt binding tye on Earth, and ſhould be alſo a Chriſtians chief ſecurity) will expoſe the Lives and Eſtates of every honeſt tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to the cruelty and trechery of ſuch profain perſons.</p>
            <p>Truly, the hopes I have that this will be rectified have induce me to beſtow this labour, in expectation, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>This written in hopes to cauſe Exciſe to be taken down,</hi> &amp;c</note> that what advance ſhall be made to the revenue will be applyed to extemate the burthen of Trade: ſo that Cloathing and other Engliſh manufactures, with the Oyls and other materials, Imported to be Imployed thereupon, will be exempted from paying the leaſt duty: whereby we may recall that Staple from <hi>Holland,</hi> and prevent thoſe ingenious Artiſts from under ſelling us.</p>
            <p>I find alſo in Mr <hi>Cradocks</hi> report a ſecond method touching Exciſe, which I remember to have ſeen pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The nature of Collecting Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in</hi> Spain.</note> in <hi>Malaga,</hi> and as I ſuppoſe is in uſe in all other parts of <hi>Spain,</hi> where in truth Exciſe is greater then in England, but Collected (in my apprehenſion) by a much properer way then with us here: for there on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two or three Officers with a Book (wherein the Marchant ſtands charged, goes to their Houſes once in 5. or 6. moneths, and taking account of all Goods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the Marchants hands give him another diſtinct charge, which being compared with his old
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39018:17"/>
account, they compute for all Goods found gone or ſold, for which the Marchant gives his bill to pay ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly at a moneth after: ſo that likewiſe by this method the Marchant is made pay Exciſe for aſmuch as he entred in the Cuſtome-Houſe: and may deliver his Goods at pleaſure, without ticket or trouble of Officers; and Oaths are not at all required. But I muſt return to the method of Beer, and Ale, which I conceive will be Collected moſt proper, and at leaſt charge by Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſes, as aforeſaid, and the Exciſe now rendred ſo Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive be accounted a more voluntary duty.</p>
            <p>That in referrence thereunto, the former Laws Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting <note place="margin">Method touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and Ale.</note> all Perſons to ſell Beer and other Drinks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Lycenſe, may be revived, and enjoyned to be duly executed; and that Lycenſes may be granted only to ſuch as the Juſtices of Peace in each County ſhall think fit and apoint at a yearly rate: unto whoſe aſſiſtance may be added a Commiſſioner, without whom nothing ſhall be tranſacted: who with a ſervant or two at moſt may be ſufficient to mannage any indifferent County according to this method, at little charge in reſpect of of what is now therein expended.</p>
            <p>That the unequallity in the Trades and draughts of <note place="margin">How all men may be juſtly rated.</note> ſeveral perſons appearing the greateſt obſticle in this deſigne, I conceive may be rectified by the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, who making it his whole buſineſs, may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf by the former receipts, or by the People themſelves, that are apt enough to inform him alſo what they paid the laſt Farmers; which together with the aſſiſtance of the ſaid Juſtices may enable them to put an equal eſtimate upon all Lycenſes, according to to the quallity and trade of the Perſons deſiring them; who will not be unwilling to pay down a quarters rent,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39018:18"/>
and give Bond yearly to be renewed, for the remainder.</p>
            <p>That no Lycenſe granted to any Perſon may extend further then for Drink ſold and ſpent in his dwelling <note place="margin">Drink ſold in Faires to pay Exciſe.</note> Houſe: So that the Drink ſold at Publique Faires, may not be exempted from paying Exciſe, but may be Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected at ſo much the Barrel, by the ſaid Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner and his ſervants, which will be of ſome uſe, if only to pay them their yearly Sallaries.</p>
            <p>That the ſaid Juſtices or any one of them, together with the ſaid Commiſſioner may have power to call <note place="margin">Power to puniſh offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> Conſtables and other Officers to their aſſiſtance in their ſeveral diſtricts; and alſo to lay a Fine or other lawfull puniſhment upon offenders (that ſell drink without Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, according to ther demerits: to be paid one Moye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the State, and the other to the poor of the Parriſh where the offence is committed: by which means the People will be made to obſerve the plain Laws by them underſtood, and be freed from that of Exciſe, often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapping them, and ſo myſtical to vulgar apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>That all common Brewers not ſelling within <hi>London,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brewers out of</hi> London <hi>to be diſcharge of Exciſe, except for ſmal Beer.</hi>
               </note> and lines of <hi>Communication,</hi> by means thereof may be diſ-obliged from paying Exciſe for all ſtrong Beer, or Ale; and a penalty be impoſed on ſuch as ſhall ſell to perſons not Lycenſed that uſually are known to tapp out or retayle the ſame: and that in conſideration of the ſix pence <hi>per</hi> Barrel laid on ſmaller Beer, the Brewer that will not compound may be made lyable to ſuch Impoſition quarterly to be paid as two of the ſaid Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Commiſſioner ſhall reaſonably calculate. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies provided, that any Brewer finding himſelf Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſuch eſtimation and ſhall together with the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of another make proof thereof upon Oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Juſtices, &amp;c. that then due allowance may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:39018:18"/>
That this way of management will not be ſo proper <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brewers of</hi> London <hi>to pay as at preſent.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>London,</hi> and lines of <hi>Communication,</hi> where the Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſerves all that is expended; and from whom the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will be collected at the leaſt charge; but as to the Country duty the caſe is much different, for their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe being paid promiſcuouſly by others as well as by Common Brewers, both muſt be kept to a ſurvey, which if done to any purpoſe, the one fourth part of the receipts will not defray the charge: by which means both the former Commiſſioners and late Farmers have been enforced to compound with all in the Country at as good rates as they could: which in effect is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod here preſcribed, dearly paid for, and brought from <hi>Holland</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> for expedition over the <hi>Alps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this may be added, that the revolutions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions of Governments ſince the Death of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Obſtructions in Goverment hinders the receipt.</note> have been great Obſtructions, to the receipts upon both Forrain and Inland duties, which are (as I conceive) augmented by giving the Cuſtome and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe but a 2 or 3 moneths continuance, and is no ſmal Intemation to Officers (whoſe places ſeem the more contingent,) and others alſo to make Hay whileſt the Sun ſhines: but apprehending the reaſon, I ſhall ſay no more, but that when the Exciſe upon all Goods is reduced to a certain ſum, and day of payment accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the methods aforeſaid, it may then be revived from one moneth to another, (if thought fit) without prejudice to the receipts; when contrariwiſe if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſubject to ſuppoſed changes, under the preſent method, the revenue will be expoſed to ruine, and many Marchants alſo receive prejudice by the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage made by others that pay little (if any duty at all:) which is, and will be a great hindrance to Trade.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:39018:19"/>
And apprehending that the Exciſe laid upon Beer, Ale, Iron, Hops, with other Inland Commodities, (not uſually exported,) is the propereſt to be continued as long as the neceſſities of State require to be ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, as being the leaſt burthen to Trade, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in uſe, with the <hi>Netherlands State,</hi> whoſe revenues is chiefly ſupported thereby. I ſhall conclude with Mr <hi>Cradock,</hi> that if leſs were laid upon many particulars <note place="margin">The benefit to the State and Common-wealth.</note> of Forrain Goods, more would be received into the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue: and that by this regulating the Cuſtome and Exciſe, the foregoing Orders and Tickets, whereby the State hath been abuſed, and ſtill are with other frauds practiſed between the Marchant and firſt buyer will be prevented: the <hi>Marchants</hi> colour of being ſo much in arreares as he hath been; (whereby the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> loſt five parts of ſix, at once of all the debts in the Nation) and no good way to this day found to make the Marchant truly accountable, will be alſo remedied, the Shop-keepers and others freed from the trouble of fetching Tickets, the revenue of Exciſe and Cuſtome be improved as may appear by the aforeſaid account two hundred and odd thouſand pounds <hi>per Annum;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides by ſuch advance of Plate may forthwith yeeld profit to the State at leaſt five Millions; and by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon all wrought Plate half a Million at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and 50000 <hi>lb. per Annum</hi> for time to come: which will diſcharge the Arrears due to the Army, and other Publique debts with a great overplus. Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in England will be alſo incouraged, Shiping and Mony increaſed, and the Exciſe Offiers ſo <hi>obnoctious</hi> to the People be taken away, the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> eaſed and the revenue be more quietly mannaged to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of all People, and Incouragement of Trade.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:39018:19"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TO the objections which ſome perhaps will make that theſe Particulars are of great waight, and therefore fit to be deferred till they may be more properly diſcourſed on, is anſwered; that what is ſaid touching Plate, may ſoon be determined, and a Revenue thereby brought in ſooner then by a monethly Aſſeſment, and with more ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Nation; and that the method here laid down for Exciſe and Cuſtome doth a breviate the Circumſtances (that occaſion trouble) and ſuperfluities (that beget charge) and brings it into a narower compaſs, and the Revenue to a greater Certainty; which if referred to a Committee Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in Trade, might be compoſed within a fortnight, and would be a moſt acceptable ſervice done in</hi> England.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
